New York Republican State Committee; Records apap119
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York Republican State Committee Records
1888-2001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap119
5.39 cubic ft. 22 reels of film, and 122 bound volumes
The New York Republican State Committee (NYRSC) is a representational legislative branch for the New York Republican Party which nominates Republican candidates for state and federal positions.
Administrative History
The New York Republican State Committee (NYRSC) is the legislative branch for the New York Republican Party. Acting as an oversight committee for all of the county committees in the state of New York, the State Committee nominates Republican candidates for state and federal positions. The NYRSC consists of a group of elected officials including at least one delegate from each assembly district. The State Committee has two parts: the main body and an executive committee that acts as the ruling body within the NYRSC. During times when the NYRSC is not in session, the executive board acts in its place [New York Republican State Committee. Rulebook for the Republican State Committee of New York State (New York: New York Republican State Committee, June 13, 1978)]. The chair of the NYRSC presides over the full committee while a separate chair presides over the executive committee. This group sends two delegates to the Republican National Convention, along with three delegates and three alternate delegates from each Congressional District and six at large delegates.
The official date set for the founding of the NYRSC is 1855, one year after the founding of the Republican Party in the United States. William Seward and Thurlow Weed are credited with the creation of the state party. In the beginning, the NYRSC met infrequently. Besides the occasional meeting during campaign time, the only mandatory meeting for the NYRSC was every three years to make arrangements for the National Convention. The Committee also did not have a written code of rules [Booraem, Hendrik V. The Formation of the Republican Party in New York: Politics and Conscience in the Antebellum North (New York University Press: New York, 1983)]. Currently, the NYRSC is required to meet following every election.
Until 1911, with the passage of the Direct Primary Law, the State of New York nominated candidates through a primary or caucus system. In the primary system, the Republican Party candidate for state and federal offices was chosen by a select few. The party voters, or those designated as official electors for each election district met several months before the primary and selected candidates for local offices and delegates to the county, assembly, senatorial and congressional district conventions. The county chairs then nominated candidates for county offices and delegates for the state committee. The average voter had little input in the choice of candidate for the various state and federal offices [Ray, P. Orman. An Introduction to Political Parties and Practical Politics (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1913.), 94].
Referred to as "machine-controlled" or "boss-controlled" politics, this system of nominating candidates for state and federal offices was considered a corrupt practice that left the majority of the voting populous of the Republican Party out of the process of nominating candidates. The electors tended to be selected from the highest officials in the Republican Party. In 1909, Governor Charles E. Hughes brought this issue to the statewide level. He believed that allowing the power to nominate candidates to rest on the shoulders of party leaders tempted them to manipulate the "party machinery" for their own gain [Feldman, "The Direct Primary in New York State", The American Political Science Review 11, Issue 3 (August 1917), 494]. The State Convention of New York had essentially become a ratifying body to support the whims of the party bosses. The current system, established in 1911 with the passage of the Direct Primary Law, allows for more input from the entire voting populous present at the primary. The party voters are allowed to choose unofficial party candidates but the rest of the NYRSC is allowed to petition this decision by writing in another candidate who can then be voted on.
In 1894, a clause in the New York State Constitution established the legislative districts in both houses of the state legislature. Fearing that the influx of immigrants would tip the balance of Democratic voters in the demographically larger New York City, the NYRSC reapportioned the voting districts in Upstate New York in such a manner that allowed more votes to be cast per voting district. This clause also stated that every county, except for Hamilton and Fulton, must have at least one member in the assembly and that no two counties divided by a river (New York, Manhattan, and Kings) could hold one-half of the seats in the State Senate [Colby, Peter W. "New York State Today", New York State Today (State University at Albany Press: Albany, 1985]. This clause had a major effect on the political landscape of New York until the U.S. Supreme Court repealed it in the 1970s with the one-person one vote decision.
In 1974, the long standing uneven distribution of voting districts that gave Republican Upstate New York an edge over Democrat controlled New York City came to an end. The United States Supreme Court ruled that the clause creating the top-heavy Upstate New York voting districts was unconstitutional. This ruling caused a massive reapportioning of the voting districts of New York. This had a profound effect on New York State politics. The Republican Party in New York lost its formidable hold on the state legislature. Most of the NYRSC's limited money went to the unsuccessful gubernatorial campaign of Malcolm Wilson in 1974. This loss ushered in a 20-year period during which the Democratic Party dominated the governor's office and the state legislature.
Past chairs of the New York Republican State Committee [Kestenbaum, Lawrence. New York Republican Party Offices [on-line index] (Ann Arbor, Michigan, 2001) 30 July 2002] include:
Edwin Morgan, 1856-1858
James Kelly, 1858-1860
Simeon Draper, 1860-1862
Henry R. Low, 1862-1863
Charles Jones, 1863-1865
William R. Stewart, 1865-1866
Hamilton Harris, 1866-1870
Alonzo B. Cornell, 1875-1877
John F. Smyth, 1877-1878
Alonzo B. Cornell, 1878-1879
Chester A. Arthur, 1879-1881
B. Platt Carpenter, 1881-1882
John F. Smyth, 1882-1883
Chester S. Cole, 1885-1887
Cornelius Newton Bliss, 1887-1889
John N. Knapp, 1889-1891
William Brookfield, 1891-1894
Charles W. Hackett, 1894-1898
Benjamin B. Odell, 1898-1900
George W. Dunn, 1900-1904
Benjamin B. Odell, Jr., 1904-1906
Timothy L. Woodruff, 1906-1910
Ezra P. Prentice, 1910-1911
William Barnes Jr., 1911-1914
Fredrick C. Tanner, 1914-1917
George A. Glyn, 1917-1922
George K. Morris, 1922-1928
Edmund Machold, 1928-1929
William J. Meier, 1929-1930
W. Kingsland Macy, 1930-1934
Melvin C. Eaton, 1934-1936
William S. Murray, 1936-1940
Edwin F. Jaekle, 1940-1945
Glen R. Bedenkapp, 1945-1949
William L. Pfeiffer, 1949-1953
Dean P. Taylor, 1953-1954
Judson Morhouse, 1954-1963
Fred Young, 1963-1973
Charles T. Lanigan, 1973-1976
Richard Rosenbaum, 1976-1978
Bernard Kilbourne, 1978-
Sandy Treadwell, 2001-2004
Stephen J. Minarik III, 2004-
Scope and Contents
The records of the New York Republican State Committee document the activities of this organization and its role as the coordinator of state and federal Republican elections in New York from 1888-1994. This record group contains meeting agendas and minutes, political literature, speeches, correspondence, photographs, political films, membership lists, and delegate information for state and national Republican conventions. In addition to the NYRSC's records, this collection also includes their reference collection consisting of several volumes that contain the names and addresses of officers in the state and federal legislature, the New York State constitution, and other volumes.
A great deal of the material was found in binders or folders arranged chronologically, so the original order has been maintained for the most part. Materials arranged under the Speeches and Correspondence Series did not fit in with a particular meeting found within the Conventions and Committee Meetings Series, so rather than interrupt the natural order of the series by interspersing items that were not originally grouped with them, it seemed more logical to put them into their own series. This series makes up the bulk of the NYRSC's records. It includes an almost uninterrupted run of minutes and agendas from 1911-1994.
Some items in the collection can be found in both bound and unbound versions. This is the case for the minutes of the New York Republican State Committee, Republican National Committee (RNC), and the Republican Organization. The minutes of the NYRSC and RNC can be found unbound covering the years from 1911 to 1994 in Series 1 and in bound versions covering the years from 1906-1928 and from 1930-1934 in oversized boxes. The New York Republican Organization can be found unbound covering the years 1908 to 1949 in Series 2 and unbound covering the years from 1908 to 1936 shelved with Series 8.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Sub-series 1: Legislative Manuals of New York, 1888, 1893-1913, 1915, 1917-1967, 1969-1970, 1973-1975, 1977-1983
Sub-series 2: New York Red Book, 1948-1982
Sub-series 3: Industrial Directory of New York State, 1949
Sub-series 4: Official Register of the United States, 1952-1953
Sub-series 5: Congressional Directory, 1953-1954, 1958-1960, 1963-1965, 1968, 1970-1971, 1983-1984
Sub-series 6: New York State Constitution, 1942, 1952-1954, 1960
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the New York Republican State Committee in July 2001.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives include the papers of Eunice Baird Whittlesey (APAP-145) and Tanya Melich (APAP-079). Consult the subject guides for the New York State Modern Political Archive and Public Servants and Politicians for a complete list of related collections.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Women; Public Servants; Elections -- United States.; Political campaigns.; Political conventions.; Presidents -- United States -- Election.; Political parties -- New York (State); Political planning -- New York (State); Campaign literature -- New York (State); Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986.; Livermore, Henrietta W. (Henrietta Wells), 1864-; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872.; Weed, Thurlow, 1797-1882.; Whittlesey, Eunice Baird.; New York Republican State Committee (NYRSC); Republican Party (N.Y.). State Committee.; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Party (N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- Convention and Committee Meetings, 1906-1994; 1; 2.8 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 includes the proceedings from New York State Republican Committee meetings. One of its most useful features is the quantity of information about legislation passed and the voting statistics for counties. These would be useful for those writing political histories; one could follow trends in voting patterns to determine how the composition of counties has changed and what issues have become more important than others. Another useful element one can find in this series is the differences of voting trends in times of war and depression. The minutes also give insight into the various personalities of those involved in state politics. The minutes are also good sources of quotations for particular committee members' stands on legislation. Many of the minutes include the current party platform, allowing one to determine how the goals of the party have changed over time. An in-depth picture of the New York Republican State Committee is available through the minutes.
  The series includes more than just the minutes taken at meetings. One also finds the original letters sent out to the various members of the NYRSC, RNC, and the county chairs. This series also contains correspondence that directly relates to specific meetings or conventions of the NYRSC and the RNC. At times one finds opinions that would not be voiced in a general meeting, so these pieces of correspondence are a good way to measure the actual tenor of the State Committee at a given time.
  The series also includes the binders used by the members of the Committee for Arrangements for the 1984 and 1988 National Republican Conventions. The binders are the first drafts supplied to delegates to the Convention. They include information on accommodations, the city in which the convention is going to take place, news and media coverage surrounding the convention, security measures to be put in place at the convention, and transportation information. These also include the minutes from the planning meetings held by the National Republican Committee before the conventions occurred.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - New York State Republican Convention, Minutes, 1911 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 1)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1920 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 1)
  - NYRSC, Minutes, 1929 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 2)
  - NYRSC, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1930 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 3)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1931-1932 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 4)
  - NYRSC, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1933-1934 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 5)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1935 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 6)
  - Committee of Finance of Republican State Committee, Minutes, 1935 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 7)
  - Campaign Committee of Executive Committee, Minutes, 1935 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 7)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Minutes, 1936 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 8)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1937 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 9)
  - Letter of Resignation of Charles D. Hilles from Republican National Committee, 1937 September 20 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 9)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1938 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 10)
  - New York State Republican Convention, First Day, Call to Meeting, Minutes and Related Materials, 1938 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 11)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Second Day, Minutes and Related Materials, 1938 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 12)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Tally of Votes, Notification Nomination and Acceptance Speech of Oswald D. Heck, Candidate for Governor of New York, 1938 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 13)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1939 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 14)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1940 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 15)
  - Republican National Convention, Delegates and Alternates, Minutes, 1940 (Box 1 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 16)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1940 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 1)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Call to Meeting, Minutes and Roll, 1940 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 2)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1941-1942 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 3)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Speeches, 1942 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 4)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Minutes, 1942 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 5)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Minutes, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1943 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 6)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1944 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 7)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1945-1946 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 8)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Speeches, 1946 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 9)
  - New York State Republican Convention, Nominating Speeches, 1946 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 10)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1948-1949 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 11)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1950 (Box 2 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 12)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1951 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 1)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1952 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 2)
  - NYRSC, Republican National Convention, Delegates and Alternates, Agenda, 1952 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 3)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 4)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1954 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 5)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1955 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 6)
  - NYRSC, County Chairs Meeting, Remarks by Nelson Rockefeller and Richard Rosenbaum, 1972-1973 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 7)
  - NYRSC, Republican National Convention, Housing Information, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 8)
  - NYRSC, Republican National Convention, Delegates and Alternates, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 9)
  - NYRSC, Delegation Votes for President, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 10)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 11)
  - NYRSC, Nomination of Candidate for U.S. Senate, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 12)
  - NYRSC, Annual Dinner and Meeting, 1976; 1980 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 13)
  - NYRSC, Republican Electors, Nominations, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 14)
  - NYRSC, Republican and Conservative Party Electors, Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 1)
  - Republican National Committee, Executive Committee, 1976 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 2)
  - NYRSC, Designating Committee, Minutes, 1978 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 3-5)
  - NYRSC and Executive Committee, Call to Meeting and Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 6)
  - NYRSC, Republican National Convention, Delegates and Alternates, Minutes, 1980 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 7)
  - NYRSC, Nomination of Candidate for U.S. Senate, 1980 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 8)
  - NYRSC, Designating Committee, Minutes, 1980 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 9)
  - Republican National Committee, Arrangements Committee, 1982; 1984; 1987-1988 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 10)
  - Republican National Committee, Minutes and Speeches, 1994 (Box 4 (1-Convention and Committee Meetings), Folder 11)
  - Proceedings of the Republican National Convention, 1988; 1992
- Membership Lists, 1896-1984; 2; 1.23 cubic ft.
  - NYRSC, 1896-1980; 2.1
    The bulk of this sub-series contains the phone and address lists for the members of the NYRSC and its executive committee, yet there are also a few lists of delegates and alternates to the Republican National Convention. These lists were handed out during meetings so that the members of these groups could remain in contact.
    - NYRSC and NYRSC Committee on Permanent Organization, Committee on Rules and Resolutions, and County Delegates and Alternates, 1896-1898; 1900; 1908; 1911-1912; 1938 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 1)
    - NYRSC, 1952 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 2)
    - NYRSC County Chairs and Vice Chairs, 1954; 1976 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 3)
    - NYRSC and Executive Committee, 1976; 1978; 1980 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 4)
  - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1908-1949; 2.2
    The Republican Organization of the State of New York gives lists of delegates and alternates to the State and National Committees. The Republican Organization of the State of New York is a quick reference guide that indicates the names of county chairs, the vote tallies for state and federal elections by county and the major resolutions passed by the State and National Committees each year. These would be excellent guides for anyone needing to find the name of an officer or the margin of votes by which an officer was elected. One could find similar uses for these sources of information as with the rolls of the State and National Committees.
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1908; 1912; 1915-1918; 1922-1928 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 5)
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1929; 1931; 1935-1942 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 6)
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1941-1944 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 7)
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1943-1947 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 8)
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1946-1949 (Box 5 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 9)
    - Republican Organization of the State of New York, 1908-1936
  - Legislature of the State of New York, 1934-1945; 1954; 1959; 1963; 2.3
    These booklets provide a quick reference guide for the legislature of the State of New York. Listed in these booklets are the members of the state legislature and a list of the members of the standing committees of the senate. These lists give the dates of service, addresses, district served, and committees on which each member sat.
    - The Legislature of the State of New York: Members, Officers and Standing Committees, 1934-1945; 1954; 1959; 1963 (Box 6 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 1)
  - Republican National Convention, 1896-1964; 1984; 2.4
    The Roll Books of the Delegates and Alternates to the National Republican Conventions act as quick reference guides for finding out who attended each convention. These booklets list the delegates and alternates along with their districts and addresses. They also give a list of the number of delegates sent by each state, a list of the Republican National Convention delegates since the founding of the Republican Party in 1856, a list of the contemporary Republican National Committee, a tally of the electoral vote by state, a list of locations for the National Convention and the candidate elected during that convention. They lend themselves to demographic studies focusing on the ratio of women delegates to male delegates that have served at the National Convention. An especially interesting study would be to compare the information found within the State rolls to the roles of the Republican National Convention.